<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Billa vera, or, The arraignment of ignoramus put forth out of clarity, for the use of grand inquests and other jury's, the sworn assertors of truth and justice.</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66895</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12733814</idno>
  <idno type="VID">66523</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240957385</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20263</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12733814</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66895)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66523)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Billa vera, or, The arraignment of ignoramus put forth out of clarity, for the use of grand inquests and other jury's, the sworn assertors of truth and justice.</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Laurence Womock. cf. NUC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66523:1"/>
            <p>Billa Vera: OR, THE ARRAIGNMENT OF IGNORAMUS.</p>
            <p>Put forth out of Charity, for the use of Grand Inquests and other Jury's; The Sworn Assertors of Truth and Justice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a LETTER to a Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. XXIV. 24.</bibl>
               <p>He that saith unto the Wicked, Thou art Righteous, Him shall the People Curse; Nations shall abhor him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:66523:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66523:2"/>
            <head>Billa Vera, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU demand my opinion of a <hi>Protestant Plot</hi> and an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Jury: 'Tis a hard province you put me upon: but I have courage enough to be honest; and if I be mistaken in my judgment, I know you have Charity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to excuse my weakness, for that reason.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Protestant Plot,</hi> I do confess, is a Title I do not well relish; because it throws a reproach upon Some sort of persons, which do no way deserve it. The word <hi>Protestant</hi> came from the <hi>Augustan Confession;</hi> and the occasion of it was taken from the close of their Address to <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fifth,</hi> wherein they <hi>Protest</hi> solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and publickly, They will adhere to that Confession, till some sedate and amicable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66523:3"/> composure of that Cause should reduce them to other Sentiments. In that Confession They openly declare, that <hi>Christians of necessity ought to obey their present Laws and Magistrates, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less they Command us to Sin.</hi> And I must tell you, the Church of <hi>England</hi> took her Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures from the <hi>Protestants</hi> of That Confession.</p>
            <p>But some <hi>Zelots</hi> of Reformation, have spread their pretensions much wider than the <hi>Protestants,</hi> and extended their attempts as far (I can not say altogether o'th' other side) as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had done before them; and never left Shuffling the Cards till they had turn'd up a <hi>Trump</hi> of their own <hi>Suite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether we have got such a sort of <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> among us, will be no hard matter to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, if we inquire a little into their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and consider their temper and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; For they must renounce the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and become <hi>Schismatics,</hi> before they can commence Rebels.</p>
            <p>Two things have deservedly brought the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> under the Reproach of Treason and Sedition: 1. Their <hi>Doctrines</hi> and profest Opinions; Principles, which dispose
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66523:3"/> the minds of Subjects for such treasonable attempts. Hereupon, when the Instigation or Command of their Superiours gives the word, They are ready <hi>prim'd</hi> to take fire, and discharge their Rebel-fury upon their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours.</p>
            <p>And (2.) their <hi>Practices,</hi> from time to time, have been so Uniform to those Principles, that the Convictions of their Guilt have been no less notorious than their perpetrations have been detestable and pernitious.</p>
            <p>And may we not observe a sort of men, that, while they pretend to abhor the <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of that Church, do never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless espouse their <hi>Principles</hi> of Disloyalty, and practice disobedience to the <hi>Civil</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? there's nothing more clear and manifest to persons that converse with Books and Modern Story. As for Matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> he that is at a loss for Evidence, let him be sent into the Kitchin among such as converse on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Soat and Smoak to light his Candle at Noon-day to seek the Sun.</p>
            <p>But besides ill principles and disaffection to the Government, this sort of men are general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of an ill temper; and because they fansy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66523:4"/> that all good nature was lost in <hi>Adam,</hi> they think it inevitable to be ill-humour'd, morose and of a peevish disposition; and then no ties of <hi>Humanity</hi> can hold, no instances of <hi>Civility</hi> can oblige them. And when this ill temper of nature meets with a little <hi>ferment</hi> of Disgust from men of another Kidney, they grow sowr and malitious, and presently set all their Wits a work to meditate revenge. And if they have got a stock of <hi>Popularity,</hi> or craft enough to be precise in their Conversation, then Religion is put on for a <hi>Cloak</hi> to their Designs, Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence fuborn'd to be a Witness, and make <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidavit</hi> of their Integrity, God himself set up to be their Shield and Patron; and then they grow bold and insolent, and the rage of their Godly Passion becomes implacable.</p>
            <p>Have we not <hi>Overt</hi> acts enough to declare these Principles and Inclinations in them? Have they not publisht the <hi>Motto's</hi> and <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols</hi> of their Sedition, and set up <hi>Raree-shows,</hi> and <hi>Banners</hi> for tokens? Are not their Tongues and Pens let loose in scandalous <hi>Pasquils</hi> and opprobrious Discourses against his Majesty? Do they not daily defame his Government, vilifie his Person, and traduce
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66523:4"/> his Actions? This has been their Practice of so long a standing, it may easily prescribe, and pass for <hi>Custome</hi> and <hi>Common Law</hi> among some of them.</p>
            <p>But now of late they have taken a greater license to be Seditious, and that they may, supplant his Majesty with more ease and a better colour, they do not only question his Right to govern and start a <hi>new</hi> Title to the Crown; but menace a <hi>Seizure</hi> of his Sacred Person, and <hi>paradigmatize</hi> his future Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Example of his <hi>Royal</hi> Father.</p>
            <p>I confess I could easily be induced (if I had no other Circumstances befor my eyes) to <hi>think</hi> such Emergencies as these, nothing else but the effects of <hi>Hot-heads,</hi> and intemperate Passions; or the rash affect of some <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents,</hi> whose ambition or avarice may have met with disappointments at <hi>Court:</hi> but when I see a violence offer'd to the proceedings and course of Law; when I cannot but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that <hi>Officers</hi> of Publick <hi>Justice</hi> do abet those very Crimes they are <hi>impannel'd</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, and stifle the <hi>Evidence</hi> they are sworn to follow, and secure the Persons <hi>arraign'd</hi> before them, by an unaccountable <hi>Ignoramus;</hi> This,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66523:5"/> I confess, seems to me, not only a <hi>Sympt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi> of a distemper'd <hi>State,</hi> but a perfect <hi>Diagnostic</hi> of some <hi>Design,</hi> a vehement pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption of some <hi>Plot</hi> betwixt the <hi>Pannel</hi> and the <hi>Parties</hi> Indicted, whom they will not think meer, or trust to be Arraign'd.</p>
            <p>I have been told of a twofold <hi>Ignoramus;</hi> the one, they call, <hi>Purae Negationis,</hi> the other, <hi>Pravae Dispositionis:</hi> An Ignorance out of a pure Negative want of Understanding, which is the Case of <hi>Ideots;</hi> or else it happens, when men are utterly in the dark for want of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi> We have good reason to assure us those <hi>Jurors</hi> were not of the first sort: the Law debars them for their Incapacity. And as we have been told, they treated the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses</hi> with so much <hi>dexterity,</hi> and put so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>nice</hi> and <hi>captious</hi> Questions to them, that their apprehensions can no way be suspected.</p>
            <p>Did they than want Information, or had they not more than they lookt for, and a great deal more then they desired? Did the Witnesses interfere or mistake in some Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of lesser moment? If they did, was it more palpable or more material, than is ufual in Evidences of this Nature? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66523:5"/> if they were not satisfied, (having before them sufficient, and more than probable grounds for an Accusation,) why did they not submit the whole business to a stricter Examination, and the Prisoner to a Legal Trial?</p>
            <p>This <hi>Ignoramus</hi> therefore is of another kind; <hi>Pravae dispositionis:</hi> Did it not proceed from an affected <hi>pravity,</hi> and an evil disposition? What Charity can free them from this Imputation? Were they not men of the same Kidney, the same Club, Livery and Faction with the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner, and so not fit to be put upon the <hi>Jury?</hi> For, being so, by that <hi>Pannel</hi> they became <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Party</hi> too; which is clearly against all the Rules of Law and Equity.</p>
            <p>But let us hear their Oath, that we may the better understand their duty; and then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve how well they did perform it. The Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their Oath is this, <hi>[You shall dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently enquire, and a true presentment make of all such matters and things as shall be given you in Charge—You shall present no man for envy, hatred, or malice; neither shall ye leave any man unpresen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for love, fear, favour, or affection; or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66523:6"/> hope of reward; but you shall present things truly as they come to your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, according to the best of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding.</hi> So help you God.]</p>
            <p>Where, we see they are bound by Solemn <hi>Oath</hi> to present things as they come to their knowledge. This excludes all <hi>Negatives</hi> and a simple <hi>Nescience:</hi> no <hi>Supernatural Inspiration</hi> is here to be pretended: no <hi>Enthusiastical</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion to be admitted: but they are to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Truth and Justice as far as the best of their Understanding can carry them.</p>
            <p>And how is their Understanding to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected? Doubtless this is to be done (1.) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Publick <hi>Fame;</hi> or (2.) by the <hi>Notorie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the Fact; or (3.) by <hi>ocular</hi> inspection and <hi>personal</hi> knowledge; or else (4.) by the <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of credible Witnesses. But I humbly conceive such as <hi>Conceal,</hi> or (which is all one) <hi>quash</hi> the Discovery of a Treason or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Crime, are, in Law, suspected to <hi>abet</hi> and encourage it.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that men of profligate Lives and Consciences, as well as those of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate Fortunes, may <hi>accuse</hi> and charge Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of known and eminent Integrity, out of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66523:6"/> malice or design, when there is no probable ground for such Accusations; and such <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments</hi> are deservedly disown'd, and ought to be thrown out as <hi>Libellous</hi> and Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Suggestions.</p>
            <p>But when the King is personally concern'd in the Indictment, (whose person is of more<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 3.</note> value with Loyal Subjects than ten thousand of themselves, and therefore so strictly guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all Laws, both Human and Divine, as well against the heart and imagination, with the tongues and pens, as against the hands and assaults of bloody Rebels and <hi>Assassines:</hi>) He is worthily supposed to carry the tenderness of a Father toward his Subjects, which always puts him in mind of his Duty to protect; and therefore abhors all thoughts, as well as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to insnare them.</p>
            <p>When a Subject therefore is <hi>Indicted</hi> for some Crime against his dread Soveraign, such a person (though cried up for never so great a <hi>Patriot</hi> among the <hi>Rabble</hi>) is not factiously or pitifully to be dismist; but to be put under so much the severer Examination. Inquiry is to be made into his Manners, and the tenour of his Conversation; what Principles he has
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66523:7"/> own'd, what Practices and <hi>Machinations</hi> he has been concern'd in, (for a wicked man is presumed to be no <hi>Changling,</hi> till he has given cleer, constant and lasting proofs of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment:) how he stands affected for the present; what <hi>Party</hi> he has espoused, what Speeches he has utter'd, and what general De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign he aims at; which will be no hard matter to determine by the means he uses to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish it. Upon such an <hi>Inquisition</hi> it will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry easie to resolve, and with <hi>moral</hi> certainty, whether the <hi>Party</hi> is to be suspected liable to such an Accusation brought against him.</p>
            <p>I do not deny but the <hi>Witnesses</hi> are to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into Consideration too; but that is more properly done upon the <hi>Trial,</hi> when the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner makes Exceptions against them (against which time they come prepared, for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, to justifie their own Credibility) but for the <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> (who have nothing to object against them, of their <hi>own</hi> certain knowledge) to be very strict and scrupulous in sifting the King's <hi>Evidence;</hi> and then to let the <hi>Accused</hi> escape without a <hi>Legal Trial,</hi> (I mean, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miss him, and not suffer him to be brought to the like Examination, (when these Witnesses
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66523:7"/> appear to be <hi>Probi &amp; Legales homines</hi>) besides the little regard it shews to the King's life and safety, it savors so rank of Faction and a sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vish <hi>Partiality,</hi> no Loyal Stomack can digest it.</p>
            <p>For if it be thus with the Prince, will it be any better with his Loyal Subjects? and if things be suffered to run at this rate, it will come to pass in a short time, that None shall <hi>suffer</hi> that be of such a Faction, tho never so guilty; None shall be <hi>safe</hi> that are against it, tho never so Innocent. And then what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of our <hi>English</hi> Liberty? Whither shall we Appeal when our Goods are rob'd and plundered, or our Lives threatned or assault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? <hi>Magna Charta</hi> will no longer be the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Loyal (for whose sole benefit it was granted) but his Snare, and the <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly</hi> of <hi>Traitors</hi> and <hi>Dissenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis very true what you alleadge, That no Oath can be taken against the King; and this shews that the Laws have a great <hi>veneration</hi> for his Majesty, and set a Sacred estimate upon, both his <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> in proceedings of this kind. But this is no prejudice to the Party arraigned; for if he has any Witnesses they are obliged to declare the Truth they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66523:8"/> know, (relating to the <hi>Trial</hi> in hand) as if they were upon their Oath; and their Testimony, always finds a valuable regard, according to the due weight and merit of it.</p>
            <p>But what they alledge must not be upon <hi>Conjecture</hi> or a doubtful <hi>Hear-say,</hi> but upon their own certain knowledge; which, how men can pretend to in Matters of <hi>Fact,</hi> unless you'l make them <hi>Ʋbiquitaries</hi> and <hi>Omniscient;</hi> or the Matter of <hi>Fact</hi> be limited to such Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> as they can po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitively say and swear they were individually <hi>privy</hi> to, cannot easily be imagined. And if they proceed upon an <hi>implicite Faith,</hi> that is no very credible practice, being derived from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and deservedly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd by all true <hi>Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in this Case, you know very well, there was no such thing as a <hi>Counter-Evidence</hi> or Cross-Examination; For the <hi>Jurors</hi> were to the Prisoner both his <hi>Vouchers</hi> and his <hi>Judge;</hi> and did deliberately Acquit him by an <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you tell me (for you leave nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faid that may make for their Excuse) that these <hi>Juries</hi> are <hi>Judges;</hi> and for some sort of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66523:8"/> them, I am very ready to acknowledge it; not only because it is the Opinion of <hi>Stephen Colledge,</hi> and <hi>John Lilburn</hi> before him; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is the Judgment of my Lord Chief Justice <hi>North,</hi> who tells that <hi>Jury</hi> (Impannel'd to try <hi>Colledge, pag. 97.) As to the truth of the Evidence, that is a question of Fact, arising from the Witnesses, and must be left upon them, whereof</hi> (his Lordship tells them) <hi>you are the proper Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is spoken of a <hi>Petty Jury,</hi> a Jury of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> which may differ much from that of a <hi>Grand Inquest;</hi> whose Duty is to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire</hi> for our Soveraign Lord the King, All Bills of <hi>Indictment</hi> are preferred to them to that effect.</p>
            <p>The Witnesses to those <hi>Bills</hi> are charged upon Oath after this manner; <hi>The Evidence which you shall give to the Grand Inquest against</hi> A. B. <hi>upon this Bill, shall be the Truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth.</hi> These Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses are sent to the <hi>Grand Inquest,</hi> or exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd in <hi>open Court</hi> before them; when <hi>They</hi> are agreed, then, upon the <hi>backside</hi> of those Bills they find true (which they always do, or should do, where they find a probable
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66523:9"/> Ground for an Accusation) they Indorse <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Vera;</hi> and thereupon the <hi>Party</hi> who stands Indicted, is <hi>Arraign'd</hi> before a <hi>Petty Jury,</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally returned to Try him,</p>
            <p>But upon such Bills as these <hi>Jurors</hi> find false (which is or should be <hi>only</hi> when there is no sufficient Ground for an Accusation), They Indorse an <hi>Ignoramus:</hi> These Bills are reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Parties never brought to Trial. And, if here be a Mistake, or a wilful <hi>Prete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition,</hi> 'tis like an Errour in the first <hi>Concoction,</hi> that will hardly admit of an after Remedy.</p>
            <p>But by these Proceedings it appears clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the <hi>Grand Inquest</hi> is obliged to weigh and ponder the <hi>Contents</hi> and <hi>Merits</hi> of the Bill, and to regard the <hi>Credibility</hi> and Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of the Witnesses; and upon a due Consideration of them both, They do either <hi>quash</hi> the Bill, as unfit to be presented, or else <hi>present</hi> it, and so promote the Prosecution of the Party.</p>
            <p>A Judgment of <hi>Discretion</hi> therefore we must allow them, and something more; for they will take themselves to be undervalued if they should not have the Honour to be reputed as Great <hi>Judges</hi> as those of a <hi>Petty Jury:</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66523:9"/> Judges therefore let them be a Gods Name in their own Capacity, provided they move not out of their own proper <hi>Sphear,</hi> nor up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another <hi>Center</hi> from the Supream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; for we are told by St. <hi>James,</hi> There are <hi>Judges of evil thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let these <hi>Will-be</hi> Judges therefore stand forth and hear their <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> from the mouth of God himself. <hi>Judges and Officers shalt thou make thee</hi> (the Law of God extends to all<note place="margin">Deut. 16. 19, 20</note> Ministers of Justice): <hi>and they shall judge the people with just judgment: Thou shalt not wrest judgment: Thou shalt not respect persons, neither take a gift. Justice, Justice,</hi> or as the <hi>English</hi> Translation reads it, <hi>that which is altogether just shalt thou follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For One that is entrusted to hold the Scales of Justice even, and to weigh all Matters that are brought before him according to their due Merit; for such a One to come into a Court of <hi>Judicature,</hi> with his <note n="a" place="margin">Mica. 6. 11. Prov. 11. 1. c. 20. 10.</note> false <hi>Ballance</hi> and his <hi>Bagg</hi> of unjust Weights, with an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> and an <hi>Epha,</hi> 'tis an Abomination.</p>
            <p>What is the false <hi>Balance,</hi> in the <hi>Moral</hi> of it, but a corrupt Conscience? What are those unjust <hi>Weights</hi> but corrupt Passions? A slavish
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66523:10"/> fear, and a foolish pity; a greedy hope, and a fond affection; a filthy Bribe, or a fawning Popularity? These are the false <hi>weights,</hi> that will turn the <hi>Scales</hi> of Justice from the due course of Right and Equity. And what is it to have an <hi>Epha</hi> and an <hi>Epha,</hi> but to measure out our respects and dealings, according to our inclinations, be they more or less, to this or the other Party? When the <hi>Indictment</hi> is for the very same <hi>Crime,</hi> and the <hi>averment</hi> made by the very same, or no less creditable <hi>Witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> to set <hi>Billa Vera</hi> upon the back of a true <hi>Conformist</hi> (who loves and obeys the Laws and Government) and to dismiss a <hi>Dissenter</hi> (who despises both) with an <hi>Ignoramus;</hi> This is an execrable <hi>Partiality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he that takes upon him to be a <hi>Judge,</hi> or if he be duly constituted to bear that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, He may as well justifie the practice of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Bribes,</hi> as that of <hi>Partiality;</hi> for indeed they are equally forbidden, and <hi>Partiality</hi> seems to be the greater fault; for <hi>Bribes</hi> are forbidden on purpose to prevent <hi>Partiality;</hi> because they may <hi>blind the eyes of the wise, and the words of the righteous,</hi> Deut. 16. 19.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Bribes</hi> are not the only Temptations
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66523:10"/> to <hi>Partiality.</hi> There are Temptations of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nature, both from <hi>within,</hi> and from <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out;</hi> tho those from <hi>without</hi> could have no effect, if they were not invited from <hi>within,</hi> and found no entertainment there; (for in this case the <hi>Receiver</hi> makes the <hi>Thief</hi>).</p>
            <p>Some are tempted and suborn'd by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate <hi>Malice,</hi> and some by a peevish <hi>Frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardness;</hi> some by a proud <hi>Ambition,</hi> and some by a sordid <hi>Avarice:</hi> some by a foolish <hi>Pity,</hi> and others by a fawning <hi>Popularity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God has thought fit to <hi>challenge</hi> all <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> that are put upon the <hi>Pannel,</hi> except the <hi>love</hi> of Justice: <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 1. 17.</note>
               <hi>Ye shall not respect persons in judgment; but you shall hear the small as well as the great; you shall not be afraid of the face of men; for the judgment is Gods.</hi> There he sets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side <hi>two</hi> at once; not only <hi>fear,</hi> but <hi>favour and affection</hi> too. As he will not have the judgment of the Poor wrested, for <hi>luere</hi> or <hi>ill will,</hi> so nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will he allow him to be <hi>countenanced</hi> in his Cause out of a <hi>Partial</hi> fondness <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 23. 3, 6</note>. <hi>Thou shalt not respect the person of the poor, nor honour the person of the mighty,</hi> (Levit. 19. 15.) Here <hi>Pity</hi> and <hi>Ambition</hi> are set aside. And <hi>Covetousness</hi> without all question is <hi>set by,</hi> in the same Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66523:11"/> with <hi>Oppression</hi> &amp; <hi>Bribery.</hi> And because <hi>Popularity</hi> swaies very much with <hi>discontented Politicians,</hi> who (being thrown out of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment) are wont to court the <hi>Multitude</hi> for their own Ambition or Security, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause not only <hi>frantick Zelots,</hi> but also <hi>jealous</hi> and <hi>well-meaning</hi> Persons, (who are easily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed upon by plausible pretences,) are apt to follow such Leaders; Therefore that crafty and aspiring Passion of <hi>Popularity</hi> is set aside as altogether unfit for <hi>Judicature. Thou shalt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 23. 2.</note>
               <hi>not follow a Multitude to do evil: neither shalt thou speak,</hi> (or answer) <hi>in a Cause, to decline af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many, to wrest judgment.</hi> He is neither to joyn in the <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> nor to <hi>countenance</hi> or <hi>approve</hi> thereof; for it is a deadly sin: but he is obliged, to the utmost of his power, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to <hi>hinder</hi> it, as his bounden duty.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Jury</hi> that acquits a Notorious <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor,</hi> and finds a man of <hi>Integrity</hi> to be Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Result of their <hi>Inquest</hi> is not a <hi>Verdict,</hi> but a <hi>Conspiracy.</hi> To pass an <hi>unjust</hi> Sentence upon the <hi>Innocent,</hi> (common Humanity will Condemn; and to <hi>absolve</hi> a presum'd <hi>Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> stands upon an <hi>equal</hi> guilt in God's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and they are both abominable; <hi>He that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66523:11"/> justifieth the Wicked, and he that condemneth the just; even they both are an abomination to the Lord:</hi> Prov. 17. 15. Against the Acquital of the Wicked, we have these Reasons from Mr. <hi>Cartwright; (1.) They always grow worse, when</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad locum.</note>
               <hi>they are absolved,</hi> (as he observes); (2.) <hi>Honest men are disturb'd and troubled at it; and sometimes are tempted to take too much Licence, from such Indulgence, to follow the lewd Example. (3.) Such wicked men as are flesht by such indulgence, are apt to run headlong into greater Crimes.</hi> But as he observes—</p>
            <p>If he who commits any <hi>one</hi> of these two Crimes of Injustice be <hi>abomination</hi> before God; then certainly He who runs desperately upon them <hi>both,</hi> provokes a greater Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against himself from Divine Vengeance. And give me leave to observe thus much to you, that They must <hi>Condemn</hi> the King, if they can <hi>Acquit</hi> the Prisoner upon such an Accusation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>It is not Good,</hi> (which is a Figure of <hi>Rhetorick</hi>) and signifies, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ill) <hi>to accept the person of the wicked, to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 18. 5.</note>
               <hi>overthrow the righteous in judgment:</hi> Much more certainly, (and how much more must
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66523:12"/> be left to <hi>decision</hi> of the Great Judge, who understands best what a value he sets upon his own <hi>Vicegerent</hi>) to overthrow a <hi>just Prince,</hi> when his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> are in jeopardy.</p>
            <p>'Tis not so small a Fault as the <hi>Vulgar</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends, to let go a Common <hi>Criminal</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out punishment; for such a one (if he be No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious) is a <hi>Common Curse;</hi> and so are they that make it their Business to acquit him; <hi>He that saith unto the wicked, Thou art righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 24. 24.</note>
               <hi>Him shall the people Curse; Nations shall abhor him.</hi> However such a <hi>Malefactor</hi> may be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by a <hi>factious</hi> headstrong <hi>Rabble,</hi> the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of sober and just men will cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him; yea, and against <hi>them</hi> too (for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging his Impiety,) and the cry of their <hi>Execrations</hi> will enter into the Ears of the Lord of <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and so much the <hi>sooner,</hi> when the just complaints of the <hi>Lord's Anointed</hi> bears them Company.</p>
            <p>Sir, you need not have askt that Question, What Measures the <hi>Jury</hi> should take in such a Case? If they had been an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> in a strict and proper sense, perhaps it had been better for <hi>them,</hi> tho no less <hi>abominable</hi> in such as <hi>made</hi> the <hi>Pannel;</hi> for taking them to be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66523:12"/> what they think themselves, and what the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulacy</hi> begins to call them; that is taking them to be <hi>Judges,</hi> in the Case, we find that of St. <hi>Austin</hi> to be most true, <hi>Ignorantia Judicis ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runque</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>d</hi> De Civit. L. 16. c. 6.</note>
               <hi>est Calamitas Innocentis:</hi> the Ignorance of the Judge is for the most part, the Mischief of the Innocent.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Ambrose</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Serm. 20. in Psal. 118.</note> gives an excellent description of a good Judge: <hi>He does nothing Arbitrary, or out of a private Resolution. He brings none of the Prejudices of his own will unto the Tribunal with him. He puts off all favour and affection, and lays aside all inclinations of flesh and blood, that he may not be prepossest or biass'd, and swerve from the Rule of Law; but conforms his Sentence to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of Just and Right. He does indulge nothing to his own Conceit: He brings nothing from home with him, that is premeditated and prepared to warp his Judgment: He follows the Laws, not oppose them, and examines the Merits of the Cause but does not adulterate or change it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have the best Example for this Practice, the Judge of all the world: <hi>Joh. 5. 30. I can of my own self do nothing; as I hear I judge: and my judgment is just, because I seek not my own, but the will of him that sent me.</hi>
               <q>Let the Judges of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66523:13"/> world learn from hence, saith the <hi>Father,</hi> with what <hi>affection,</hi> what <hi>sobriety,</hi> what <hi>sincerity</hi> they should approach the Seat of Judgment. He that is <hi>Omnipotent</hi> can do nothing by his <hi>Power,</hi> but governs himself by his <hi>Integrity</hi> in a Case of Judicature. The Duty is so Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, He indulges nothing to his own will in it, but devotes himself solely unto Justice; <hi>As I hear I judge; and my judgment is just, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause</hi> I follow the Rule and Laws <hi>of him</hi> who put me into <hi>Commission. Quasi homo loquitur, quasi judex docet:</hi> Christ speaks like a man; but teaches like a Judge; for he that judgeth<note place="margin">Idem Ibid.</note> must not follow his own will, but the course of Law and Justice.</q> But the <hi>unjust Judge</hi> does otherwise: <hi>Pilate</hi> says not so, [<hi>As I hear I judge</hi>] makes no such Profession: But <hi>usurps</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riry at another rate, <hi>Joh. 19. 10. Knowest thou not that I have power to crucifie thee, and have power to release thee? Pilate</hi> is here taken by the words of his own Mouth, (saith that <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi>) The <hi>Laws</hi> of Justice are not his Rule, but his <hi>Power:</hi> And by that <hi>Power</hi> he <hi>condemn'd</hi> the Prince of Peace; and by that <hi>Power</hi> He <hi>acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> that very Person, who had made a <hi>Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in the City, and committed <hi>Murder</hi> in the<note place="margin">Luke 23. 19. Mark 15. 7.</note> heat of his Insurrection. Was this according
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66523:13"/> to Conscience, to the Rule of Equity, or the Law of Nations?</p>
            <p>A Judge is to proceed according to his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, <hi>Secundum Allegata &amp; Probata;</hi> not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Conceit, or human per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion; wherefore the <hi>Clerk</hi> calls upon <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> to attend and to <hi>hear their Evidence;</hi> which were to no purpose, if they were allowed to govern themselves by any preconceived <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice,</hi> either against the Person or the Truth and Honesty of the Witness. For he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es as a <hi>Publick</hi> person (and so should all <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> act) for his King and Country; wherefore he is obliged to follow, not the <hi>Notions</hi> he has as a <hi>private</hi> person, but to govern himself by the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Customs</hi> of his Countrey, by such <hi>Informations</hi> and <hi>Notices</hi> as come to him regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly upon the account of his <hi>Office</hi> and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. If a Judge should be allowed to do otherwise, a <hi>Gap</hi> would be set open to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the <hi>Innocent</hi> as well as to free the <hi>Guilty:</hi> The people would learn to <hi>despise</hi> the Laws, and have the course of Justice in Contempt by such examples; the <hi>tranquility</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> would be disturb'd, and all the <hi>Foundations</hi> of the Government would be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66523:14"/> out of Course, as the Learned <hi>Lawyers</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suists</hi> do observe.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>One</hi> Case, and but <hi>one,</hi> that I have met with, wherein a Judge may <hi>decline</hi> the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> which is given, and not proceed upon the Matters alledged and <hi>judicially</hi> prov'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: that is, when, according to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Course of Law,</hi> he should take away the life<note place="margin">Cas. Cons. L. 5. c. 54. §. 21.</note> of a Man, <hi>Quem evidenter novit esse Innocentem,</hi> whom he does <hi>evidently</hi> (and not by conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture or good opinion only) <hi>know to be Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> as <hi>Amesius</hi> states it. For example, <hi>A. B.</hi> is arraigned for Murder; the Allegations and Proofs produced are strong &amp; clear to make him Guilty. Tho the Witnesses be never so <hi>positive</hi> in their Assertions; yet if the Judge knows the person Accused to be <hi>free</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent;</hi> if he knows He was then <hi>Absent,</hi> or else observed him <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>unconcern'd</hi> in the quarrel, and saw <hi>another</hi> person commit the Murder: upon this his <hi>certain knowledge</hi> of the Matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> neither <hi>Law,</hi> nor <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> will allow him to give Sentence upon such an <hi>Innocent</hi> person, but he is obliged to use his utmost <hi>diligence</hi> and <hi>interest</hi> to rescue him from false Accusers.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:66523:14"/>
            <p>But this is so far from the Case in hand, that had <hi>Amesius</hi> been alive, he would have commenced <hi>a fresh Suit</hi> against such an <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus,</hi> with as much heat and vigor as ever he did against the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I speak now of this <hi>Grand Inquest,</hi> as they are lookt upon in the quality of <hi>Judges:</hi> And Judges we know, have not long since, been <hi>impeacht,</hi> for <hi>Illegal, Partial,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> proceedings. If these <hi>Jurors</hi> will put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> with Judges, they must be content to take the like fate with them, when they are observed to do amiss. For their offence is of a higher and more exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Nature; and being, at least <hi>forty</hi> for <hi>one,</hi> more diffused, 'tis so much the more perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and if a timely Remedy be not apply'd, 'twill spread so fast and so far, as to grow <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidemical,</hi> and Corrupt the <hi>Justice</hi> of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And now the Practice is so bold as to affront the King, no man can expect better measure from such <hi>Pannels,</hi> unless he be a <hi>Bird</hi> of the same <hi>Feather;</hi> For 'tis evident, that among the several ways and methods of <hi>discovering</hi> a <hi>Criminal,</hi> two at least, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66523:15"/> and supprest by this means. For you must give me leave to expostulate the Case with you.</p>
            <p>1. Was there no <hi>Colour,</hi> no <hi>probable ground,</hi> no <hi>sufficient</hi> matter for an Accusation? Was not the <hi>Indictment</hi> for Crimes of as deep a <hi>dye</hi> as those for which others have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servedly <hi>Condemn'd?</hi> Was not the <hi>Evidence</hi> as full, cleer, and every way as sufficient, both for <hi>weight</hi> and <hi>number,</hi> as the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires? Were not some of the Witnesses the very <hi>same,</hi> and all of them of as good <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute</hi> and <hi>Credit,</hi> as those that serv'd the turn, without dispute, in <hi>other Cases?</hi> Durst not those <hi>Jurors</hi> trust the Prisoner to be tried by <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Countrey?</hi> Or durst they not Trust him to <hi>Himself,</hi> lest the presence of his Accusers, and the force of their Charge, face to face, should <hi>sting</hi> him into a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction,</hi> and melt him into so much <hi>Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> as to <hi>Confess</hi> the Fact, to discover the <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociation,</hi> and betray a <hi>Common Guilt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there not such a <hi>Proclamation</hi> as this made at the <hi>Arraigment</hi> of a Malefactor? <hi>If any man can inform my Lords, the Kings Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Kings Serjeant, or the Kings Attorney,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66523:15"/> or this Inquest to be taken between our Soveraign Lord the King, and the Prisoner at the Barr, of any Treason,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>let them come forth, and they shall be heard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who can tell but some <hi>Shy</hi> or <hi>Modest</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses might have taken Courage to shew their <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> had they seen the Prisoner thus <hi>legally</hi> Arraign'd, and brought to <hi>Trial</hi> in good earnest?</p>
            <p>These <hi>two</hi> ways of discovering the Crime, that is to say, 1. By the <hi>Confession</hi> of the <hi>Party</hi> upon Conviction; and 2. by such <hi>Evidence</hi> as might have come in upon <hi>Proclamation;</hi> were prevented and supprest by this <hi>Ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> And it seems, The <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> nay the very <hi>Life</hi> of our <hi>Dread Soveraign,</hi> which was pretended to be so <hi>deer</hi> and <hi>preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> to us, when 'twas threatned and endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd by the <hi>Papists,</hi> is now become so <hi>low</hi> and <hi>cheap,</hi> in our esteem, when it is like to be <hi>sold</hi> or made over into the hands of a Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Republicans,</hi> that 'tis not so much as to be Considered, or put into the Balance, when the life of <hi>one</hi> of that <hi>Party</hi> is call'd in question.</p>
            <p>You are pleased to ask me, Would you
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66523:16"/> not have them go according to their <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi> Yea, with all my heart. But if we duly weigh the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> we shall easily discern that this is but a <hi>futilous</hi> and <hi>putid</hi> Allegation; For Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence has no such <hi>Franchise Royal,</hi> as some of late have made it; it gives us no <hi>priviledge</hi> to do what we list; for it is a kind of <hi>Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storian Constitution;</hi> there is a <hi>Judicature</hi> set up in it; and the <hi>proceedings</hi> and <hi>Office</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in exercised, are thought to be best and most aptly set forth by the Parts of a <hi>Categorical</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amesius Cas. Consc. l. 1. c. 1. §. 7, 8.</note>
               <hi>Syllogism;</hi> wherein the Law makes the <hi>Major</hi> Proposition after this manner, <hi>Every Traytor ought to be brought to Condigne punishment:</hi> The Evidence makes the <hi>Minor</hi> thus: <hi>This Person</hi> A. B. is a Traytor; And when these <hi>two</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions are laid together, A Good Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can never fail of a right Conclusion. And let me talk never so demurely, when <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> is made nothing but a <hi>Faction,</hi> Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can be nothing else but <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> or <hi>Pretence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I perceive you think it a great piece of <hi>Charity;</hi> and if it were an <hi>Errour,</hi> you tell me, it was an Errour of the <hi>right hand,</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66523:16"/> so the more excusable: But, Sir, <hi>Charity</hi> must not appear upon the <hi>Bench</hi> to obstruct the Justice: God gives her no such <hi>Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 16. 20.</note> She is to be no <hi>Advocate</hi> in a Case of <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature,</hi> when a Matter is upon <hi>Trial;</hi> how far soever she may obtain <hi>Audience</hi> when the Trial's over. And be the Errour on which hand it will, there lies a <hi>Writ</hi> against it in the <hi>Court</hi> of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Nor will the pretended Charity to a <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi> Person compensate the Mischief of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice done to the <hi>Community.</hi> In such Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of a perverse <hi>Inquest,</hi> there is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of more and more grievous Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages than possibly you may imagine.</p>
            <p>For you must always remember, These <hi>Jurors</hi> are under Oath, not to <hi>Conceal</hi> any thing that shall come to their knowledge, for <hi>Fear, Favour,</hi> or <hi>Affection, Reward, Gain,</hi> or <hi>Hope;</hi> but to present the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>the whole Truth.</hi> Now in doing otherwise</p>
            <p n="1">1. They <hi>violate</hi> this <hi>Oath;</hi> and turn the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of Truth into a <hi>Sanctuary</hi> for Transgressors. And if it be certainly true (as most certain it is) That for <hi>rash</hi> and <hi>common</hi> Oaths the Land <hi>mourn;</hi> much more for the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66523:17"/> breach of <hi>Solemn Ones,</hi> and most of all, when this is done by the <hi>Ministers of Publick Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They <hi>frustrate</hi> the <hi>end</hi> of such <hi>Civil</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions; They <hi>rescue</hi> a <hi>common Pest,</hi> a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor from <hi>condigne punishment;</hi> which may bring a <hi>common Guilt</hi> upon the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They leave the <hi>Person</hi> of the Prince <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed</hi> to the <hi>Machinations</hi> of a Traitors Malice, whom such <hi>Indulgence</hi> will <hi>animate</hi> to the greater danger of the King, and perhaps the <hi>Ruine</hi> of the Kingdom,</p>
            <p n="4">4. They <hi>defame</hi> the <hi>Witnesses,</hi> and lay the foulest blot upon <hi>them</hi> that can be imagined; They give occasion to make the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That they are <hi>suborn'd</hi> and <hi>perjur'd</hi> men, of no <hi>faith</hi> in their Averments, of no use in a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> nor fit for any trust in <hi>Civil Conversation.</hi> And if this be according to the Law of <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>doing as we would be done by,</hi> (which is the Law of Christ) The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of such <hi>Inquests</hi> must be content to have their own Reputation <hi>Meted</hi> out by the very <hi>same</hi> Measure.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They incur the <hi>Guilt</hi> of all those <hi>Crimes</hi> charged in the <hi>Indictment;</hi> For tho 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66523:17"/> They were not of the <hi>Cabal,</hi> or admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the <hi>Cabinet,</hi> to give the <hi>Advice;</hi> yet they <hi>abett</hi> the practice by <hi>Consent,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty by the <hi>venome</hi> of <hi>Adhaesion</hi> in a tacite <hi>Concealment</hi> of the Fact, and removing the <hi>Criminal</hi> out of the way of <hi>Trial</hi> that he may <hi>escape</hi> the hand of <hi>Justice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What you say more for their Excuse seems to carry a suspition, that you think them of the same <hi>Party</hi> with the <hi>Accused;</hi> and no man is bound <hi>to accuse himself.</hi> But I must take leave to tell you, He that knows himself <hi>Guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less</hi> may take a <hi>voluntary</hi> Oath to <hi>acquit</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and <hi>assert</hi> his own <hi>Innocency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, if he be put upon the <hi>Pannel,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts the Office of a <hi>Juror,</hi> you know he is sworn to make a true presentment, not only of all such <hi>Matters, Articles,</hi> and <hi>Things</hi> as are given him in <hi>Charge,</hi> but also of such <hi>other Matters</hi> and <hi>Things</hi> as shall <hi>come to his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> touching the present Service. Having <hi>accepted</hi> this Service (from which he might have <hi>excused</hi> himself) He is <hi>bound</hi> by his Oath (as he makes it <hi>voluntary</hi> by not declining it) <hi>to discover the whole Truth</hi> he knows, tho he finds <hi>himself</hi> involved in the guilt; and in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66523:18"/> Course of Justice, where any <hi>Conscience</hi> is left, it is no unusual thing to find <hi>Confitentem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> a Guilty Man his own Accuser.</p>
            <p>Sir, to conclude your trouble with my own, I cannot dissemble my Opinion, That such as stickle so eagerly to release <hi>Barrabbas,</hi> if it were in Their power, They would easily <hi>deliver up</hi> Jesus <hi>to be Crucified.</hi> For if you well observe it, <hi>That</hi> was done by a kind of <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Jury: So much is imply'd in our Saviours Prayer for them: <hi>Father forgive them;</hi> for <hi>They know not, what they do;</hi> Indeed their <hi>Ignorance</hi> was not <hi>invincible</hi> but <hi>wilful</hi> and <hi>affected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their <hi>Zeal</hi> made them <hi>Mad,</hi> and their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice blind,</hi> and both together kept them <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> of the things which belonged to their Peace. Their fear of the <hi>Roman Yoak</hi> made them Conspire against their <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 2. 2.</note>
               <hi>Native King: Venient Romani,</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> will come; That<note place="margin">John 11. 48.</note> was the pretence: But <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19. 14.</note> We will not have this Man to reign over us, was their stubborn Resolution.</p>
            <p>The fruitless <hi>Figg-tree</hi> was mark't out for the <hi>Symbol</hi> both of their <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Punishment,</hi> and became a <hi>Prolusion</hi> to Gods <hi>dereliction</hi> of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66523:18"/> Them under the <hi>Course</hi> of a <hi>Sacred</hi> barenness. After several severe <hi>Essays</hi> of his Displeasure without any <hi>Remedy</hi> or <hi>Effect,</hi> at last (<note n="*" place="margin">King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. murdered <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1648. which is 33 years since. <hi>Deus avortat Omen.</hi>
               </note> and that within less than <hi>Forty</hi> years) <note n="†" place="margin">1 Thess 2. 15, 16.</note>
               <hi>The wrath of God came upon them to the uttermost.</hi> And through their damnable <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> against Heaven, and their restless <hi>Mutinies</hi> and <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> against their Governours, Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance brought upon them their own <hi>Fears:</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> came in good earnest, and <hi>took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way both their Place and Nation:</hi> lest them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>City</hi> nor <hi>Temple,</hi> neither <hi>Priest</hi> nor <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> neither <hi>Prince</hi> nor <hi>Government.</hi> Their Kingdom was of <hi>this World,</hi> and whatever They might pretend, They look't no <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> And if we reflect upon Their present Circumstances, They are <hi>skilful</hi> only to get <hi>Wealth,</hi> but a common Execration among all Nations.</p>
            <p>And this was the sad Fate of a <hi>Jerusalem Ignoramus.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 Cor. X. 11, 12.</bibl>
                  <p>Now all these things happened unto them for Ensamples: and they are written for our Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66523:19"/> upon whom the Ends of the World are come.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore let him that thinketh he standeth, take heed lest he fall.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>